<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Solace for saints in the saddest times from the consideration of the happy temperature and lovely composure of all times and providences as to Gods glory and their good : held forth in a brief discourse on the first words of the Canticles / by Joshua Sprigg.</title>
            <author>Sprigg, Joshua, 1618-1684.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1648</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 45 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A61192</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S5075</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28871</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10772207</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10772207</idno>
            <idno type="VID">45784</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A61192)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 45784)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1410:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Solace for saints in the saddest times from the consideration of the happy temperature and lovely composure of all times and providences as to Gods glory and their good : held forth in a brief discourse on the first words of the Canticles / by Joshua Sprigg.</title>
                  <author>Sprigg, Joshua, 1618-1684.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12], 39 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Giles Calvert,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1648.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Print show-through with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Song of Solomon --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:45784:1"/>
            <p>Solace for SAINTS in the SADDEST TIMES. From the Conſideration of the happy temperature and Lovely com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſure of all Times and Providences, as to Gods glory and their good. Held forth in a brief Diſcourſe on the firſt Words of the <hi>CANTICLES.</hi> By JOSHUA SPRIGG, M. A. ſometimes Lecturer in Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermary, London.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Giles Calvert,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the ſign of the black-ſpread-Eagle, at the Weſt end of <hi>Pauls</hi> 1648.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:45784:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:45784:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, MY Honored good LADY, the</hi> Lady Willougby, <hi>Wife to the Right honorable the</hi> Lord Willoughby <hi>of PARRAM.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Madam,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen I deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh this Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, Your Honour came firſt to my thoughts
<pb facs="tcp:45784:3"/> as in dedicating it to whom I could only <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieſce.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Not that Your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour had any <hi>ſpeciall</hi> title to it, by <hi>hearing</hi> it or <hi>deſiring</hi> it; but my hope is there may be more <hi>providence</hi> in it then my <hi>own,</hi> who am ambitious to <hi>ſeal</hi> up ſome <hi>teſtimony</hi> of the high eſteem I have of Your Honour, to whom I am <hi>oblieged,</hi> as by ſo much <hi>Worthineſs</hi> of Your
<pb facs="tcp:45784:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> own, ſo by many <hi>favours</hi> received.</p>
            <p>Madam, I queſtion not but you have your part in <hi>Afflictions</hi> as a Daughter of <hi>Adam,</hi> and not the fewer as a Daughter of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> You may have need of a <hi>Cordiall,</hi> and then Providence will be remarkable in ſending <hi>This</hi> to you; and I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire you may ſee your <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt</hi> in this Conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: if you be <hi>ſtrong</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45784:4"/> and feel no ſinking of Spirits, it is through the <hi>Experience</hi> of this Truth which is here de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed.</p>
            <p>Madam, I have ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable thoughts of you, and great deſires on your behalf, and therefore ſhall no longer by this intertainment keep you from ſwifter injoyments then while I commence this ſuite for you, That, as not a few have born away the <hi>fruitfulneſs</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:45784:4"/> of <hi>your</hi> Diſpoſition in the <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> of their own ſpirits, ſo your Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour may be abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſatisfied and refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the gracious <hi>preſence</hi> and <hi>appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> in all his <hi>diſpenſations.</hi> In this moſt humble ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of himſelf accept, Madam,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors moſt affectionately devoted, as much Obliged Servant, JOSHUA SPRIGGE.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:45784:5"/>
            <head>A VVORD TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Diſcourſe being delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſome years ſince (when the publike affairs appear'd moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plext and dangerous) is now publiſhed upon the very ſame account and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion it was firſt Delivered, with ſome hopes it may be
<pb facs="tcp:45784:5"/> ſome way ſerviceable, (through the preſence of Chriſt with it) to demulce and aſſwage ſome to a quiet and peaceable Comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with the preſent ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration, by diſcovering and ſetting before them a new and bleſſed face and Image in every (even the worſt) ſtate of things.</p>
            <p>The ground and matter I work upon being thoſe firſt words of the CAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICLES; my project riſes by rendring the title of the book not onely to the form of words but to the ſubject matter of it: which (viz. the matter) being all varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
<pb facs="tcp:45784:6" rendition="simple:additions"/> of diſpenſation to the Churches, may teach us a new Arithmetick to caſt up Times and Things by.</p>
            <p>The condition of many a Man is like a good Old Inſtrument that is hung up by the Wals, as of no uſe for want of tuning onely: or like a Leſſon that is ſo muſicall, that onely skill is wanting to make admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Muſick of it: where the Spirit of the Lord is, there is Muſick.</p>
            <p>I have followed the Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy or Reſemblance (of Divine workings and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence to a Song) but in ſome generall Parallels on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb facs="tcp:45784:6"/> it might have been pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted through many more particulars.</p>
            <p>The Diſcourſe had not the ſucceſſe to be Well-un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood when it was deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, it may have the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter bleſſing to empty down upon the Reader.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:45784:7"/>
            <head>The Order and Parts of the Enſuing Diſcourſe.</head>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Introduction,</hi> by ſhewing the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of this diſcourſe, <hi>viz.</hi> a project to comfort Saints in every appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of things, and the fitneſs of the ſubject for ſuch a purpoſe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Explication.</hi> 1. The ground and matter whereupon the Project ſtands, <hi>viz.</hi> the Comparing the name of this book of <hi>Canticles</hi> with the ſubject matter of it. 2. An inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie into the ſubject matter of the book of <hi>Canticles.</hi> 3. A report of the ſubject matter, what it is, <hi>viz.</hi> A Propheticall Hiſtory and Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricall Prophecy of all the times of the Church.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The <hi>Obſervation.</hi> That this is a Song, yea the Song of Songs.</p>
            <p>1. The Remarkableneſs of putting ſuch a name on ſuch a thing, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in reſpect of the ſeverall ſad Notes that are in this Song.</p>
            <p>2. The proof of it yet to be a Song, yea
<pb facs="tcp:45784:7"/> the Song of Songs. 1. By the matter of it. Variety it ſelf. 2. The form <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitie.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The <hi>Application</hi> and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of this truth.</p>
            <p>1. <hi>Information,</hi> All Gods admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations to beleevers, publique and particular, are as a Song; yea ſecondly, a Song of Songs.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A Song, the Analogy opened in ſeverall particulars. 1. A Song conſiſts of meaſured feet. So all Gods adminiſtrations are foreſeen weighed, and meaſured, though not alwayes the ſame meaſures, and the reaſon of that difference aſſigned from the ſeverall times and ages of the Children.</p>
            <p n="2">2 It is a Song of Songs. This ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to Chriſts adminiſtration in three reſpects.</p>
            <p>1. The variety that is in it.</p>
            <p>2. The Rhyme or ending of all: One thing rhyming to another, and in the end all ſounding alike, even Love. 3. The Elegan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies and glorious contrivances that are therein.</p>
            <p>2. <hi>Dehortation,</hi> 1. Not to look with ſuch diſmall apprehenſions on
<pb facs="tcp:45784:8"/> Chriſts adminiſtration, publicke or private, however it appear, ſeeing tis a Song. 2. Not to be wearie and impatient.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Exhortation,</hi> 1. To ſing this Song, <hi>(i.)</hi> with lightſome hearts, walk with God through all providences. Motive, 1. The burden of the Song is Love. 2. the Contrivance is Gods, for the glory of his deareſt Son; and his Spouſe the Church. 2. Exhort. ſo to obſerve this Song <hi>(i.</hi> the workings of Chriſt for us) as to be turned into ſuch a mind and ſuch actions as pleaſe Chriſt.</p>
            <p>4. <hi>Direction,</hi> To reconcile us to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Adminiſtration. To that end let us. 1. Compare the parts together. 2. Cover the uncomely parts with cleanly notions. 3. Conſider our acceptableneſs to God in every change and condition.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:45784:8"/>
            <head>CANT. I. I. <hi>The Song of Songs.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y deſign, in chooſing this Text, is, to oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curr and prevent (if it be not too late) that <hi>weakneſs</hi> which the unbelieving fears of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God may bring them into, of the like dangerous Conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, as the loſing of blood and ſpirits. The Cure of fear is Faith; but for as much as to the exerciſe of Faith Men had need have cleer and compoſed ſpirits, therefore have I pitched upon this Subject.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:45784:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Saul</hi> was often troubled with an euil ſpirit (a sickly, hair-braind, raging ſpirit) and that which did him eaſe, was <hi>Davids</hi> playing upon a Harp before him. And <hi>Eliahs</hi> ſpirit being muddied, as it were by paſſion, cannot Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie til the mud was ſetled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain by a minſtrel. 2 <hi>King</hi> 3. 15. The ſpirit of the world, either carnal love, or fear, or any other paſſion, is like the evil ſpirit that troubled <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Eliah</hi> — and faith is as Prophefying; Now when the hand of the Lord; whereby we beleeve comes upon us, the other hand, whereby we are troubled is taken off us; the ſpirit of faith comes not but the ſpirit of the world muſt be caſt out, as <hi>Hagar</hi> and <hi>Sarah,</hi> the bond-woman and free-woman, could not live together; and you ſee <hi>muſick</hi> was the inſtrumental means in thoſe caſes. Therefore
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:45784:9" rendition="simple:additions"/> I have choſen a Subject of this nature, in the diſcourſing where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, if the Lord Jeſus, the wiſe charmer, make me by his ſpirit to charm wiſely, I hope it wil be in ſome meaſure conducible to the end propoſed. <hi>A Song of Songs, which was Solomons.</hi> So that I deſire you to bear me wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I do it not out of reſpect to the time of the yeer, <note n="*" place="margin">It being a feſtivall time when this Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon was preached.</note> which is with unreaſonable ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on preferr'd by too many; but to the times of the Church, the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions and neceſſities of the Saints, which call for all the help of this nature that we can make, I mean to hold up their ſpirits in the preſent carriages or miſcarriages of things; and the truth that this Text travells of, bears no ſmal proporrion of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducibleneſs to this end; and were it but cleerly underſtood, ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly believed, and effectually ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:45784:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> to you by the ſpirit of Chriſt, it would be like <hi>a bun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle of mirrhe between your brests,</hi> the virtue whereof is, that is preſerves from corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and infection, and <hi>a cluſter of Camphire</hi> which makes men <hi>vegetiores et firmiores,</hi> as <hi>Pliny</hi> obſerves.</p>
            <p>Here therefore, I ſhal not ſpend time about the diviſion of this Text into the <hi>Title,</hi> and the <hi>Authour</hi> of the Book. But the Notion or Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion I ſhal preſent to you at this time, and preſs upon you, is, from comparing the <hi>name</hi> of this Book with the <hi>ſubject</hi> mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of it: The name is, <hi>A Song of Songs,</hi> The Subject matter, what is that? There are divers opinions of this, chiefly three: Some make the Subject to be the mutuall and reciprocall ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings out of affections and fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:45784:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> between Chriſt and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Beleever.</hi> 2<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. Others be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Chriſt and the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> or generall Aſſembly, from the beginning to the end. 3<hi rend="sup">ly</hi>. A third ſort of Interpreters, make it a brief, compendious Propheſie of the mutuall carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges and aſpects, of Chriſt and his <hi>Churches,</hi> (the <hi>particular</hi> Churches of the Goſpell, as wel as the Church of the <hi>Jews,)</hi> from <hi>Solomons</hi> time to the end of the world. And though there be (as a <note n="*" place="margin">M. <hi>Cotton</hi> of Boſton in New England.</note> reverend Divine well ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves) a holy and uſeful truth in the two former; yet this latter might be convinced to be the more <hi>adaequate</hi> ſcope and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of this Book (by many Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, if it were our buſineſs now) which doth exceedingly commend this Book to us, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a <hi>Prophetical history,</hi> and Hiſtorical Propheſie, giving us
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:45784:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> a brief and delightful view of all the acts and <hi>Monuments</hi> of the Church, (of particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in their ſeverall and ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive times,) and this book is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a Song. This is that which is remarkable, that ſuch a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject ſhould make a Song. You wil ſay, wherein lies the remar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kableneſs? Herein: If this be a compleat and a perfect Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie (as it is) of all times, then it muſt record as wel the <hi>evil</hi> times of the Church, as the <hi>Halcion</hi> days; and the <hi>defections</hi> of the Church, as wel as her <hi>perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons;</hi> Gods <hi>chastening</hi> diſpenſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as wel as his <hi>affectionate</hi> embraces; his <hi>frowns</hi> as well as his <hi>ſmiles;</hi> his <hi>placking up</hi> of Churches, as wel as his <hi>planting</hi> of them, the <hi>calling</hi> off the <hi>Jews,</hi> as wel as the <hi>calling</hi> of the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles. And that this ſhould be fit matter for a <hi>Song,</hi> ſeems ſtrange
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:45784:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> I beleeve: As if one ſhould write the ſtory of Gods dealing with <hi>England</hi> from the firſt Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to the preſent, or to the end of the preſent agitations, &amp; cal it a <hi>ſong;</hi> you would think it an unfit name: though we have had much mercy, yet you would think that the Denomination ſhould rather follow <hi>deteriorem partem,</hi> and it ſhould be more proper to call it the <hi>Lamentation of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> (that is fallen from ſuch a height of peace and proſperity) then a <hi>Song,</hi> yet are there as ſad times as theſe recorded in this book, yea, and worſe, (not only theſe but others, worſe I ſay;) for here <hi>Solomon</hi> by the ſpirit of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie touches the very <hi>tops</hi> and eminent points of <hi>all</hi> times that ſhould ſucceed from his own, yet this he, by the holy Ghoſt, cals a Song, yea, <hi>a Song of Songs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. to ſhew you this in ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:45784:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> that there are very <hi>dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful notes</hi> in this Song. 2. That yet it is a <hi>Song.</hi> 3. What uſe we ſhould make of this.</p>
            <p>For the 1. to inſtance but in a few things, in the beginning of this Propheſie: Firſt, you have the <hi>blackneſs</hi> of the Church, through the <hi>defection</hi> of <hi>Solomon,</hi> who <hi>kept not his own vines</hi> (his own <note place="margin">v. 5. I am black.</note> wives from Idolatry;) and yet this is one particular that goes to this Song. 2. You have the <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion</hi> of the Kingdom, the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volt of the 10. Tribes, from the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> (for <hi>Rehoboams</hi> ſtifneſs and folly) <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>My mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers children were angry with me.</hi> 3. You have the ſad eſtate of the faithful, diſperſed through thoſe 10. Tribes in that revolt: in what diſtreſs were they to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>void Idolatry, and to enjoy the pure Ordinances of God, while they could not injoy their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:45784:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> without expoſing them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to one of theſe great evils, either the wrath and <hi>perſecution</hi> of <hi>Jeroboham,</hi> if they ſhould not go up to the <hi>Calves</hi> but to <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> or elſe they muſt forſake their habitations of a ſudden; perhaps to their undoing! This was a ſad ſtrait, yet this is part of the Song. <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>Tell me, oh thou whom my ſoul loveth, where &amp;c.</hi> Then, 4<hi rend="sup">ly</hi> You have the ſad eſtate of <hi>Judahs</hi> falling away from God, (as after 3 yeers of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoboam</hi> they did) then God ſent <hi>Pharoah Shiſhack</hi> King of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> to yoke them. 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 12. 8. This you have, <hi>v.</hi> 9. and ſo I might run through the next <hi>Chapter.</hi> In the 16. <hi>v.</hi> of this 1 <hi>Chap.</hi> you have a commendation of the Houſe and Worſhip of God, that it was pure and <hi>green,</hi> yet <hi>v.</hi> 1. of <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>I am the roſe of Sharon,</hi> whether you take it of <hi>Chriſt</hi> or
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:45784:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> the <hi>Church;</hi> though <hi>Joſiah</hi> had made the <hi>bed green</hi> by his Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, yet <hi>Chriſt</hi> comes not to his ſpouſes <hi>bed,</hi> but rather cals his Church <hi>abroad. Sharon</hi> was an open field under <hi>Lebanon,</hi> where the beaſts did feed; Or take it of the <hi>Church,</hi> ſhe was the <hi>Roſe of Sharon.</hi> There was no <hi>fence</hi> nor <hi>culture,</hi> weeds might grow up with her, or the beaſts of the field might crop or tread her down; and ſo it was you know: <hi>Joſiah,</hi> how fair a Roſe, but how ſoon cropt by <hi>Pharoah Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cho;</hi> and the ſucceeding Kings were placed and diſplaced by the <hi>Babylonians</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians,</hi> at their pleaſure; and at length the Kingdom was laid waſte by the <hi>Babylonians;</hi> yet this is part of the Song, and ſuch is the compoſure of the whole book.</p>
            <p>But I may not inſtance in any more; but as it is in the world,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:45784:13"/> there are <hi>hills</hi> and <hi>valleys</hi> all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the earth, ſo is it in this hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory; as you have hills of emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent proſperity, ſo there are val<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leys of dark adverſity; yet this is called a Song, and that moſt properly, yea, <hi>A Song of Songs;</hi> as we might ſhew in 4. reſpects, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Author,</hi> the <hi>Matter,</hi> the <hi>Form</hi> and the <hi>End;</hi> but the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, and the end, I ſhal decline for brevity; it may be, I may touch upon them in the uſe. The matter and form of this moſt excellent Song, is expreſt in theſe two words, <hi>Variety</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity;</hi> variety is the matter; there are various things ſpoken of various conditions, yet theſe are made up into one; unity is the form. 1. Variety is not repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to the nature of a Song, to have for its ſubject, Gods various diſpenſations to the Church, and the Churches various affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:45784:14"/> condition and converſati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards God. <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Evil</hi> days, though they <hi>diſagree</hi> in <hi>themſelves,</hi> yet may make up a <hi>Song together:</hi> Here in this Song is all the variety that may be; all that was or will be, ſince <hi>Solomons</hi> time, to the worlds end, is here couched together. Though a deluge of darkneſs and ignorance hides the particulars of Gods great works from our eyes til they are done, (as the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters did the old world,) yet the tops of the Mountains may be ſeen here.</p>
            <p>2 Here is <hi>Unity</hi> in this variety; all thoſe ſeveral and various (Yea we may think contrary) paſſages, conditions and times, ſerve to make up one compleat piece of <hi>poeſie</hi> or invention, and one glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious piece of adminiſtration; for there is ſuch a contexture of them, and they are ſo diſpoſed,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:45784:14"/> that in ſtead of fighting one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt another, and contradicting one another, they do mutually <hi>illustrate</hi> and ſet off one another. The Painters colours, ſhould he ſhake them and <hi>mix</hi> them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in a pot, he would loſe them all, they would fight one with another, and would either be no perfect colours, or but one, but being layd on a table by the art of the <hi>Painter,</hi> they ſerve for excellent uſe, and are exceeding beautiful. So it is here, the <hi>mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries</hi> and <hi>mercies,</hi> the <hi>defections</hi> and <hi>perfections</hi> of the Church, being layd and diſpoſed by ſo skilful a penſil, as is the hand and wiſdom of God, make up a ſight exceeding glorious.</p>
            <p>Now what Uſe may we make <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> of this, that God hath compoſed the affairs of the Church into a Song; certainly the Song is not its own end; God did not expreſs
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:45784:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> them in this form, for the form ſake, as if he were more deligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with a Song then <hi>Proſe,</hi> or as if we ſhould be taken with the expreſſion, and look no further: There is a <hi>truth</hi> that lies under the <hi>expreſsion;</hi> and this outward expreſſion; (I mean the form and words of this Song) is but a weak ſhadow of the inward truth. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam</hi> put names upon the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, according to their natures, and God gives outward forms to the creatures, agreeable to their ranks; the moſt excellent out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward form to man, becauſe he hath the moſt excellent inſide, therefore he hath received a more comely and beautiful out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide; and the Angels, becauſe they come more near to pure Intelligences and to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of God, then men, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if they have any outward form (as ſome think it is neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:45784:15"/> they ſhould (none being ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely ſimple but God) yet it is very ſubtile and ſpiritual. <hi>So</hi> 
               <note place="margin">The Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>then, Gods meaning in expreſsing thoſe things, the affairs of Christs Kingdom, in all times, by the name and in the form of a Song, is to tell and teach us, what a notion we ſhould have of theſe things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, cloathed with this form, and called by this name, that the ſeries and ſubſtance of them is as a Song, or is that analogically in a way of reſemblance, that this form of words is properly.</hi> Therefore is the <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription</hi> of theſe things, a Song, becauſe the <hi>things themſelves</hi> are ſo: As, therefore is the picture beautiful, becauſe the face, in imitation or expreſſion whereof it is made, is beautifull. I ſhal ſhew this <hi>analogy</hi> between the <hi>affairs</hi> of Chriſts Kingdom (contained and tranſacted ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively and orderly) and a <hi>Song,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:45784:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> in ſome particulars; and herein Iſhal take in other conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, beſides what the <hi>Hebrew Songs</hi> do afford, for ſo this ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject wil give me leave, which is <hi>a Song of Songs,</hi> what ever thing is delightful or admirable in any <hi>Song,</hi> (I mean in the <hi>Songs</hi> of any language) is in this.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Then the univerſall and common nature of all Songs re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, that they be of meaſured feet, of ſtrict numbers, every line conſiſts of ſo many mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, therefore they are called <hi>metra:</hi> All Poems are not alike for feet and meaſures; every language differs from others and hath variety in it ſelf, and your <hi>Lyrick</hi> poems (ſuch as <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes and this book is) have a greater liberty then other kind of verſe, their feet and meaſures being very much arbitrary, more or fewer in a verſe, as the compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:45784:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſhould chooſe, but <hi>numbers</hi> there are in all, though ſomewhat latent from us. Now what would the Lord teach us hereby, but that all the affairs of his Church are foreſeen in his Counſell: all their times and changes, mercies and miſeries, the adminiſtration of Chriſts Kingdom, is a ſet form, even as a <hi>Song</hi> is; it cannot vary a Title from the Counſel of God, no more then a verſe can without lameneſs or hobling. <hi>Known to the Lord are all his works</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 15. 18. Epheſ. 1. 11.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. He worketh all things accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Counſel of his wil.</hi> Gods wil, which hath an infinite varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it, is determined by his Counſel, <hi>(q)</hi> So for particular believers, all the tranſactions that concern their ſouls, are a known, certain, and unvariable form: Chriſt hath ſet how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny temptations, and how long; how many afflictions, and how
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:45784:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> long; how much knowledg and holineſs; what ever befalls them, from the beginning to the end of their days, their ſins cannot hinder any good determined from co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in its order, place &amp; time, nor can bring any evil upon them unſeaſonably or uncertainly, but as the feet &amp; meaſures of a <hi>Song,</hi> ſucceed orderly, whereby the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity thereof is preſerved, ſo it is here, God hath not left him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf room to inſert one bleſſing more then he purpoſed from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity (nor needs he) nor left himſelf liberty to crowd in one Croſs, more then went to the making up of the <hi>Song:</hi> But as <hi>Lyrick verſe</hi> hath a greater ſcope for variety and uncertainty, then other Poems; ſo doth the Lord ſhew a great liberty in his admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations, both publike and private, it is <hi>verſe,</hi> as if it were not: God obſerves numbers, as
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:45784:17"/> if he obſerved them not, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceals his art from us, at leaſt wiſe. He is not bound, that this part of the Song that is now ſinging, ſhould have the ſame meaſures that was 2000, years ago, or to deal with his Church, or particular beleevers, now, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the ſame Tenor that he did formerly: Becauſe he did not ſpare <hi>Iſrael</hi> for thoſe ſinnes that are rife amongſt us, ſhal we ſay he cannot ſpare us? I might inſtance in many things, wherein God hath vindicated his liberty already; and for particular be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers, there is a manifeſt diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence profeſſed by the Lord him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his pen-men, in his carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age to us and former beleevers. <hi>We are come not to the Mountain</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4. 1. Heb. 11. 40. Heb. 12. 18.</note> 
               <hi>&amp;c. Better things are reſerved for us:</hi> We are not children in non-age, but heirs grown up, and ſo we have more love and grace,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:45784:18"/> and are leſs ſnib'd then they: God is not bound to lead us about in the wilderneſs, as he did them; Nay, <hi>he hath promiſed to ſhorten his work in righteouſneſs.</hi> Rom. 9. 28. So that, though Chriſt ſpins a long thread of patience, yet at length, and even on the ſudden, he will cut the thread: agreeable to <note place="margin">Eſa. 10. 22. The con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption upon the earthly, Antichriſti<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>an Church State, ſhal overflow of a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, as the deluge of the old world.</note> this, ſome think that this laſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion that is going upon the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Thouſand</hi> of yeers, ſhal not be above 700 yeers, yet as much and more ſhal be done in this ſpace, then in any 1000. before; for as all things draw neerer their Center and period of their mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, they make more ſpeed. Thus the times and things of the Church, and of each particular beleever, are a <hi>Song,</hi> both as they are contrived and acted by Chriſt.</p>
            <p>2. It is <hi>a Song of Songs;</hi> here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, I ſhal take in ſome Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:45784:18"/> not eſſential to al Songs, or the Songs of all languages; though the <hi>Hebrew</hi> hath a reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blance of all the delightful pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties of any kind of Song (the <hi>Hebrew</hi> and our <hi>Engliſh</hi> have greater ſtore of theſe properties I ſhal mention, then any lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage) I ſhal inſtance but in 3. things. 1. The Variety that is in ſome <hi>Songs.</hi> 2. The Rhime. 3. The Elegancies. Firſt, it is the commendation of a <hi>Song,</hi> if it be of a <hi>delightful,</hi> pleaſing ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, and variety is a great com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation, and beſtows much delightfulneſs upon a ſubject, when the invention is <hi>copious</hi> and <hi>various,</hi> when there be various perſons and various parts acted by thoſe perſons various times, tempers, conditions; as this is the ſnare of <hi>Romant's</hi> (invented ſtories) they have ſuch a pleaſing variety of paſſages and accidents,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:45784:19"/> as ſteal away too much time and heart from thoſe that read them; why, here is all the <hi>variety</hi> in the world, in Chriſts and the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches actions, ſweetly tempered and ſubdued to a delightful har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony, all is an exchange of <hi>love,</hi> between Chriſt and his Church, but here is ſometimes <hi>amantium irae,</hi> and then <hi>redintegratio amo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris,</hi> ſometime Chriſt making love to his Church, and <hi>ſlighted</hi> by her, then the Church as much in love with Chriſt and as little <hi>ſatisfied;</hi> ſometimes the husband caſts his wife into <hi>priſon,</hi> and then fetches her out and ſets her upon a <hi>throne:</hi> My beloved, the variety of conditions that the Church appears in, as in ſeveral dreſſes, is like <hi>Joſephs</hi> Coat of many colours, commends the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery the more (being ſubdued and tempered as before,) even as many flowers of a various co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:45784:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> and ſmel, bound up in a po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie are more delightful, and do catch the ſenſe more then any <hi>ſingle</hi> flower; or as many colours curiouſly diſpoſed by a skillfull penſil, make up a lovely picture, which one colour alone would not do, and as that is the chief inſtrument which hath <hi>most ſtrings,</hi> and that the beſt muſick that is playd upon <hi>most ſtrings,</hi> and that the beſt leſſon that hath moſt <hi>diviſion,</hi> ſo is it here: The myſtery of Chriſts Adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to his Church, were not ſo beautifull, were it all of a colour, were it all plain work, though all proſperity &amp;c. No, but a ground work of <hi>black,</hi> ſets off the <hi>brighter</hi> colours with a greater grace, ſo doth the Churches Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity, the Churches Proſperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and her <hi>ſtraits</hi> inlarge her <hi>mercies,</hi> the <hi>Long ſuffering of our Lord is Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="24" facs="tcp:45784:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>So for particular believers, there is a <hi>variety</hi> in their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons outward and inward, and this is the excellency thereof; there is <hi>hope</hi> and <hi>fear, comfort</hi> and <hi>diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, health</hi> and <hi>ſickneſs, temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations</hi> and <hi>inlargements, ſin</hi> and <hi>grace;</hi> and the ground-work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing laid in theſe black colours, ſin, and deſertion, and affliction &amp;c. the light, and life, and love of Chriſt are illuſtrated hereby; ſin <hi>abounds,</hi> grace <hi>ſuper-abounds;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 5. 20. 21.</note> they are caſt down and laid low with temptations, raiſed high w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> conſolations. That ſhip mounts up neereſt to the heavens that hath its viciſſitudes of deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding very low, by reaſon of une<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual waves. <hi>Jam jam tacturos tartara</hi> &amp;c. <hi>jam jam ſydera ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma;</hi> their prayers are the better, their love the ſounder, their faith is more exerciſed. Thus you ſee, how Chriſts adminiſtration is as
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:45784:20" rendition="simple:additions"/> a lovely Song, the ſubject where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is variety it ſelf; and this the Lord would have us to conſider, when he calls it <hi>a Song of Songs,</hi> and would have us delighted with it as he is, and if we could but get up to the top of ſome mountain to ſee all the variety, and how it is ordered and diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed beautifully, it would ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour us: what variety of diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation hath there been ſince God made <hi>Adam,</hi> and put him in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radiſe! We ſee man up &amp; down, and up again, what then is the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety of the whole miſtery, which though we cannot ſee diſtinctly and particularly, yet the Lord hath given us an abſtract of it, <hi>(q)</hi> in the Propheſies, though a deluge hide the particulars! And thus the Lord would have us to look upon one time and paſſage with another. If you look upon a moſt beautifull pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:45784:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> and look upon one colour of it, eſpecially if it be the ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt and darkeſt, there is no beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in it; but ſet the whole <hi>varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> in your eye, and then it is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightful; So let your eye be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Churches <hi>beauty,</hi> as wel as her <hi>blackneſs;</hi> look on the <hi>iſſue</hi> God gives out of temptation, as wel as his action in <hi>leading</hi> into temptation.</p>
            <p>2. There is <hi>Rhime</hi> in ſome Songs, and herein the <hi>Hebrew</hi> doth Symbolize with the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> more then the <hi>Greek</hi> or <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> do; Rhime is when <hi>one line anſwers another in ſound,</hi> as wel as in number of feet; Thus God makes one time or age to Rhime to another, one Chriſtians heart, condition, temptations to Rhime to another; our <hi>Chaſtiſement</hi> to Rhime to our <hi>ſins,</hi> that ſuch a ſin is ſuited in the Chaſtiſement; <hi>returnes</hi> of mercies to Rhime to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:45784:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> our <hi>prayers,</hi> Rhime makes the Song the more pleaſant, though the matter be but ordinary, and this commends the adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Chriſt, that it is all <hi>har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony,</hi> all Rhime <hi>(q)</hi> croſſes and mercies, ſins and duties altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>All work together for good,</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom. 8. 28</note> through the love of Chriſt, the love of Chriſt makes the ſame <hi>ending</hi> of all his diſpenſations, they ſound all alike, and that ſound which ends all, is <hi>Love.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. Songs do, in a more emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent manner, glory in the <hi>Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of all manner of <hi>ellegancies,</hi> then proſe. As <hi>Metaphors, ſimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litudes, tropes</hi> and <hi>figures,</hi> and moſt amiable <hi>reſemblances,</hi> taken from <hi>Jewels, ſpices,</hi> and <hi>vineyards, Orchards, Gardens, Wineſellars,</hi> and the chiefeſt beauties, and greateſt varieties of al the works, both of God and man; the Songs in Scripture are the eleganteſt
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:45784:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> parts of Scripture, <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Deborahs</hi> Songs &amp;c. Agreeably, the Adminiſtration of Chriſts Kingdom is full of <hi>elegancies,</hi> and they that have ſpiritual <hi>eyes,</hi> and <hi>eares</hi> that can <hi>try words,</hi> do admire them: what elegancies in bring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt!</hi> it is ſaid, he <hi>bare them upon Eagles wings;</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Deut. 32.</note> Eſpecially now in theſe latter days; this part of the Song that is now fulfilling abounds herein. What <hi>high ſtrains</hi> of providence &amp; <hi>neat contrivances!</hi> Every other <hi>work</hi> is an <hi>elegancy.</hi> The actions of our enemies are nothing but <hi>Ironies;</hi> they ſpeak evil againſt us, but it is intended againſt themſelves; <hi>The wicked is inſna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in the works of his own hands:</hi> the <hi>Biſhops</hi> made <hi>Cyphers,</hi> inſtead of making the Parliament ſo. Look abroad amongſt the <hi>Turks</hi> and <hi>Indians,</hi> where Chriſt hath no viſible Church nor peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:45784:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> and there is no ſuch <hi>needle-work</hi> of providence, and ſo it hath been from the beginning. Gods <hi>name</hi> therefore hath been <hi>great in Iſrael,</hi> only in <hi>Iſrael;</hi> The Lord <note place="margin">Pſal. 76. 1 Pſa. 99. 2.</note> would not have us think, only, that things are adminiſtred in a juſt way, but in the moſt comely, excellent and <hi>heroical</hi> way. That which the <hi>wiſe Ladies</hi> of <hi>Siſera's</hi> Mother, are ſuppoſed to ſay of <hi>Siſera's</hi> prey in <hi>Deborah's</hi> Song, may be ſaid of the adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or providence of <hi>Chriſts</hi> King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, the whole piece of it. <hi>It is a prey of divers colours, of divers colours of needle work, of divers co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lours of needle work fit for the necks of them that take the ſpoyl;</hi> Chriſt is not content to provide things <hi>wholſom,</hi> but through the inlar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gedneſs of his heart, he makes all <hi>toothſom</hi> for his Church; we have not only <hi>meat</hi> but <hi>ſauce.</hi> For this way he hath choſen to make
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:45784:23"/> known his <hi>manifold wiſdom,</hi> and to unfold it. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 3. 10. And beloved, that particular belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers do not obſerve ſo much in Chriſts <hi>private</hi> adminiſtrations to them, is long of their <hi>eyes.</hi> There are Chriſtians, that ſhould another write the hiſtory of Chriſt and their mutual carria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges (which are tranſient, and lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle heeded by themſelves, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps) they would admire them, &amp; be exceedingly delighted there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with; how Chriſt governs their ſpirits, anſwers their prayers, ſubdues their corruptions, exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes their graces, the lively and lovely <hi>touches</hi> in all theſe, could they be deſcribed by a pen, would even proceed to a raviſhment of the heart of whoever ſhould un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand them. The elegant ways that Chriſt hath to <hi>fall</hi> off, and <hi>come on</hi> in his love, his <hi>cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtning</hi> and <hi>cheriſhing</hi> love.</p>
            <pb n="31" facs="tcp:45784:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Therefore let us not look with <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</note> ſuch diſmal apprehenſions upon Chriſts adminiſtrations, publike or particular, <hi>It is I,</hi> ſays Chriſt, <hi>be not affraid;</hi> ſo I ſay it is a <hi>Song,</hi> therefore be not affraid, Chriſts heart was in <hi>love,</hi> in the original <hi>invention</hi> of it, and ſo it is in the immediate and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular <hi>acting</hi> of things, it is a <hi>love-ſong,</hi> a <hi>marriage-ſong,</hi> for ſo they were wont to have Songs at their weddings in former times, and when the Churches marri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age with Chriſt is ſolemnized [who is now eſpouſed] then ſhal this Song be ſung with <hi>underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> and unſpeakable delight. <note place="margin" type="runSum">
                  <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe.</hi> 2.</note>
            </p>
            <p>2. <hi>Be not weary and impatient,</hi> we do not uſe to be weary of hearing a delighful Song; Songs have that advantage above proſe, that they ſteal away the eare with a great deal of pleaſure. Certainly, if you did but heare
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:45784:24"/> the melody of this Song, and did diſcern the curiouſneſs of the compoſure: I mean, could you perceive the ſweet, ſpirituall ſtrains of Divine working in and <note place="margin">Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers ſay, If we could hear the muſick of the <hi>ſphears</hi> we might live upon it.</note> for the Church, and particular believers, we ſhould not need to crave your patience. Why be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved, if you do not underſtand nor admire it your ſelvs, through your dulneſs and heavines, yet give the <hi>Lord</hi> leave to <hi>ſing out his Song;</hi> have that civility and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to him: <hi>Chriſt</hi> is <hi>taken</hi> with it, therefore there is great <hi>worth</hi> in it; The long ſuffering of the Lord is ſalvation: if it were not a lovely Song, Chriſt would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>doaze</hi> himſelf with ſinging of it.</p>
            <p>3. <hi>Let us ſing this Song,</hi> as we find the Church ſinging ſome parts of it. <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. 9. &amp; 14. 3. and 15. 3. You may ſee there what the Song is, and who they are that
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:45784:24" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſing it, ſuch only as are <hi>redeemed from the earth, [i.]</hi> either ſuch as are truly <hi>ſanctified,</hi> or more ſtrictly ſuch as are redeemed from the <hi>earthly Kingdom</hi> of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> and indeed none but ſuch can ſee a beauty and a glory in the adminiſtrations of Chriſt, none but ſuch can rejoyce in them. Therefore I call only up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſuch; you that are the <hi>Lambs wife,</hi> ſing this Song with light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome hearts, obſerve all the ways of Chriſt with your ſpirits, how he walks towards you in outward and inward things, what <hi>strict meaſures</hi> and <hi>proportions</hi> he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves in your temptations, that they be not above your maſtery; and in your comforts, that they be not too ſtrong for you neither; obſerve the variety and change that is in your hearts, temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, conditions, converſations, in Chriſts diſcoveries, and manife<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:45784:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> of himſelf to you, and <note place="margin">Oh how amiable a ſight it is to ſee bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren live together in unity; but more admirable to ſee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries &amp;c. This is the glory of Chriſts ſcepter it reconciles the Wolfe and the Lamb, the Lyon and the Kid.</note> how harmoniouſly theſe <hi>work to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether,</hi> for your good and Chriſts glory, when he makes himſelf the more welcom to you, by kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping from you ſometimes; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve what muſick his hand makes by touching <hi>contrary</hi> ſtrings <hi>(q)</hi> he ſtrikes a <hi>baſe</hi> and a <hi>treble</hi> together: many times the <hi>publike</hi> note is <hi>high,</hi> and thy <hi>par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular low;</hi> a ſpiritual mercy and an outward croſſe ſtrike to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, or an outward mercy and an inward temptation: Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve how <hi>certain</hi> and unmovea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your <hi>happyneſs</hi> is: the whole Song would be ſpoyled and run <hi>lame [q]</hi> if one particular, that God hath determined, ſhould miſcarry: therefore your ſins and infirmities ſhal not be able to hurt you: nay theſe together with your afflictions, are part of the Song; <hi>I am black but comely,</hi> I
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:45784:25" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſpeak not this, that you ſhould ſlight ſin, or not watch againſt it: no, he that hath taſted of the grace of Chriſt, will <hi>not ſin that grace may abound,</hi> though he <hi>loves that grace well.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us ſing this Song with lightſom hearts, with grace in our hearts; <hi>David</hi> had Songs of pure adverſity of his <hi>deep waters,</hi> but here is more ſweet then bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in our conditions, whether publike or private.</p>
            <p>1. Remember the <hi>burthen</hi> of the Song is <hi>Love: ſo God loved his Church</hi> (and ſo thy ſoul) muſt be brought in at the end of every ſtaff, yea at the end of chaſtning: <hi>Whom I love, I rebuke and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>2. The Angels have begun the Quire, when Chriſt was firſt ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted, <hi>glory to God in the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>3. It is a Song worth our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:45784:26"/> for it was penned by the beſt wit that ever was, even the <hi>wiſdom of God</hi> himſelf. It was framed for the <hi>glory</hi> of his <hi>deareſt</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Can we not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſuch affection read the tragicall fiction of ſome one dying for a deare friend, or the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween two paſſionate lovers, the ſeveral hard for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunes they ran for one another, with one another; and have we no af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections for theſe more reall parts and tranſacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons?</note> 
               <hi>Son, and his ſpouſe the Church,</hi> in whom he ſo delights. We love to ſee ſuch paſſages <hi>acted</hi> in a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or a ſhew: why ſhould we not much more be taken with this <hi>real</hi> Song? If the invention of the Father himſelf, could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive a ſweet and glorious piece, then this is ſuch. <hi>Can we he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted</hi> [ſays one] <hi>to hear a heathen Poet ſing a fabulous ſtory of Hercu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les,</hi> their great Champion, go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down to Hell, and bringing thence the <hi>Lady Proferpina,</hi> and ſhal we not take more pleaſure in hearing of Chriſts deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding into the grave for us, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covering his Church out of the hands of Death and Hell.</p>
            <p>I have one thing more to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend unto you, and that is that
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:45784:26" rendition="simple:additions"/> you would ſo obſerve and ſing this ſong, I mean, be ſo taken with the workings of Chriſt for us, and in us, as to be <hi>turned thereby into ſuch a mind, and into ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions as pleaſe Chriſt. Hiſtorians,</hi> and <hi>Poets</hi> tell us wonderfull ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of Songs and Muſick upon hearers; how <hi>Amphion</hi> with the muſick of his Harp, <hi>drew ſtones and trees</hi> together for the buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of <hi>Thebes.</hi> Oh now that my diſcourſe this day of this Song, or rather your <hi>reall ſence</hi> of the ſweetneſs of it, might draw you together as <hi>materials</hi> for the <hi>new Jeruſalem,</hi> that your bodies, your ſpirits, your purſes, your pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, your word and deed might all be ready for advancing the honour of Chriſt and your own happyneſs, in the preſent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns! You wil ſay, ſhould we <hi>give all for a Song,</hi> then we were fools indeed? My beloved, it is
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:45784:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſuch a Song, as God the Father, and Chriſt, and the Angels ſing, and are delighted with continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and to hear how the Saints ſhal ſing it one day in the <hi>kingdom</hi> of their Father, wil be a torment to thoſe that are ſhut out of this Quire, and provoke their how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. To reconcile you to the preſent adminiſtration, I name but 3 things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Compare</hi> and lay together <note place="margin">I am black but come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. v. 5.</note> one paſſage with another, one ſtring makes no muſick.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Cover</hi> the unpleaſant and uncomely parts, with cleanly names and notions, as we do in our bodies, put <hi>moſt honour</hi> upon thoſe parts that have <hi>leaſt</hi> in themſelves: thus the ſubjection of <hi>Judah</hi> to <hi>Pharoah</hi> is ſet forth by an heroical expreſſion. <hi>v.</hi> 9. of this <hi>Chap. A company of horſes in Pharoahs Chariot:</hi> a Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent expreſſion of ſervitude, not
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:45784:27" rendition="simple:additions"/> Aſſes but Horſes, not Jadesina Cart, but Horſes in a Chariot, yea a Kings Chariot.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider your <hi>acceptable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs</hi> to <hi>God</hi> in every paſſage, time, change or condition: Chriſt loves you as wel in your <hi>night gown;</hi> as in your <hi>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious dreſs,</hi> as in the verſe fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentioned. I have compared thee O my love, to a company of Horſes: <hi>I have compared thee;</hi> Thou haſt ſold thy ſelf thither, but I have put glory upon that condition, for thy ſake: I have compared thee, <hi>O My Love, My Love</hi> ſtill, though a ſlave, a <hi>Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> to <hi>Pharoah!</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <p>Imprimatur</p>
            <closer>
               <date>
                  <hi>Novem.</hi> 12. 1647.</date>
               <signed>Joſeph Caryl.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
